This is the Wattieza tree.
Widely believed to be thefirst tree that ever existed.
Fossils showthat it appeared on Earth
around 385 millionyears ago
when life on land was just beginning to flourish.
But if we wind back the clock justa bit more
Earth looked very different.
Therewere no lush forests, no soil,
and grass wouldn'texist for another 300 million years.
It was almostimpossible
for anything to survive on land.
Sowhere did trees come from?
Despite this desolatelandscape,
there was one strange form of
life thattowered over everything.
These are prototaxites.
Giant living organisms that once stood up to 25 fttall.
Although they look like early trees,
thesemysterious creatures weren't trees at all.
Insteadof being made from an
organized network of longwoody fibers,
prototaxites had a messy networkof interwoven tubes.
Unlike trees,
they didn't usephotosynthesis to survive
and instead got all oftheir nutrients from the ground.
Because of this,
scientists generally thought
they were some kindof giant fungus.
But a recent study of a prototaxite fossil
showed that the organic compoundsleft behind
had no resemblance to fungi at all.
In fact, it seems like prototaxites were
an entirely different form of lifealtogether.
For millions of years,
these thingsdominated the landscape
and helped pave the way
for trees to eventually take over.
But how?
Atsome point in Earth's history,
all life existedin the ocean.
Without soil or nutrients,
land was an impossible place to survive.
But deep inside the rocks,
the nutrients neededto support life did exist.
It was just a matter ofgetting them out.
With the help of waves
complexlife forms like fungi and algae
got pushed closer to the water's edge
and started tosettle on the rocky shores.
From there
the fungi used their powerful acids
to break downthe rock and
release the nutrients trapped inside.
The algae used these nutrients to grow
and in exchange gave the fungi special sugars
that it made through photosynthesis.
The two organisms had formed
a close symbioticrelationship
and started spreading furtherinland.
Over time, the fungi and algae
eventuallydied and decomposed,
leaving behind a loose, thin layer of organic matter.
TheEarth's surface now had the key ingredient thatwould allow life to explode onto the land...
Soil.
Not only was it full of nutrients,
it acted likea sponge,
allowing water to be stored inside.
Italso provided the perfect base
for algae to anchoritself to the soil.
For the first time in Earth'shistory,
plants that were trying to grow
on landdidn't have to mine the rock.
Thenutrients were right there, ready tobe used.
Because of this,
the fungi and algaestarted to conquer the land,
building on the soilthat
previous generations made before them.
Thesetiny organisms were about  to evolve
intoevery single plant and tree we've ever known.
Butbefore that happened,
they made this ad from Odoo.
Odoo is an all-in-one business management platform
that offers entrepreneurs more than 45 apps
tohelp with managing their business.
From sales,invoicing, accounting,
website creation,and so much more.
What makes Odoo really powerful
is that all the apps are integrated
in onecentralized platform,
so you don't wastetime juggling
external tools or programs
that don't work together.
Do you have a business
or a project that needs a website?
Odoo has youcovered.
With Odoo's website builder app,
you can get a brand new website
up and runningin just four simple steps.
First, define yourwebsite type, industry, and goals.
Then, choosea color palette or upload your logo.
Then,finish it off by selecting an overall theme.
Once your site is up, editing it
becomes easyand intuitive.
Simply drag and drop contentblocks,
then modify everything like text,
colors, images, buttons, and more.
Each elementcan even be
animated with dynamic effects,
making your site feel premium.
With Odoo, thefirst app is free for life,
includingunlimited hosting and support.
You also get a freecustom domain name for 1 year.
After that,as your business grows,
you can easily add moreapps when you need them
and have access to allapplications
at an affordable subscription.
To get started with Odoo,
check out the linkin the description.
In order for the first life onland
to go from algae to the first ever tree,
someevolutionary breakthroughs had to happen.
Althoughit wasn't optimized for the
dryness of land andthe intense sunlight,
very gradually the algaestarted to evolve.
Its cell walls grew thicker
andit developed a waxy outer layer
to stop the waterfrom evaporating.
This however, made it much harder
for the algae to absorb carbon dioxide
which itneeded for photosynthesis.
To get around this,
it developed tiny little pores
that couldbe opened and closed
to let the carbon dioxidein
and to let oxygen out.
Instead of relyingon a single egg to reproduce,
they developedtiny spores at the top of the plant.
These wouldget carried by the wind,
land much farther away,
and grow into a brand new plant.
By this point,the algae was no longer algae.
It had evolvedinto an embryophyte
with tiny leaflike surfaces toabsorb light
and roots that helped anchor it into the soil.
Bit by bit, these moss-likeplants
started spreading further inland,
butwithout direct access to water,
surviving becamealmost impossible.
Once again, they had to evolve.
At the bottom of the plant,
dead cells startedto collect and form into small lumps.
Eventually,these grew more and more,
pushing the leaf higherand
forming a hollow tube below.
Inside the tube,
water could now be stored
and transportedall the way from
the ground up to the plant'sleaves.
More tubes started branching off fromthe main stem.
And eventually, we arrived atthe
first plant with its own plumbing system,
theCooksonia.
No longer did it need to be
directly ontop of a water source.
Instead, it couldspread out
and conquer the land much more easily,
finding pockets of water and
maximizingits sunlight capture.
But these tubes also gavethe plants some strength,
and for the first timeever,
plants started to fight gravity andgrow upwards.
This started the height war that
would eventually lead to trees.
With moreand more plants
fighting for the same resources,
a plant that grew taller than its neighbors wouldguarantee itself more sunlight
while alsoshading its competition.
On top of that,
the reproductive spores from a taller plant
wouldtravel farther in the wind,
allowing it to quite literally spread
its seed farther than any otherplant.
But growing tall wasn't easy for theseearly plants.
The vascular tubes that carried the
water were soft and thin.
The taller the plantgrew,
the more weight it had to support.
If theywanted to keep growing taller,
they needed a muchsturdier material.
They needed wood.
Luckily, longbefore algae left the water,
it had developed acrucial ingredient called lignin,
which protectedit from the sun's intense UV radiation.
But whenplants started conquering land,
the lignin started bonding together and turning
the softplant stems into sturdy, wood-like structures.
Thisbreakthrough was about
to turn plants into giants.
But amazingly, one form of life beat them all toit.
The prototaxites.
While every other plantwas
just starting to reach a few inchestall,
prototaxites had already
established acompletely separate
but almost identicalcopy of lignin.
This allowed them to grow
intoenormous living beings
and that had a hugeimpact on the soil.
Their enormous networkof inner
tubes would have loosened upthe soil,
allowing oxygen and water to get in
and making it more fertile.
Whenever a prototaxitedied,
it would decompose a huge amount
oforganic matter back into the ground.
They weren'talone, but prototaxites
acted as massive soil producers,
laying the foundations for the
forests that were about to take over.
Eventually,
the lignin in plants caught up
and these wood-likestems started
reaching far beyond the heightsof prototaxites,
finally evolving into the Wattieza tree.
At this point, trees started taking over
and lush forests began colonizing
Earth'ssurface, reaching far beyond 100 ft tall.
Treeshad well and truly won the evolutionary race,
and prototaxites eventually went extinct.